A Register of the Anna Howell Hayward Lisle Papers
Hoover Institution Archives
Anna Howell Hayward Lisle Papers
1934-1957
circa 2001
2005C64
Lisle, Anna Howell Hayward, 1908-2001.
2 manuscript boxes (0.6 linear feet)
Hoover Institution Archives Stanford, California 94305-6010
Anna Howell Hayward Lisle worked with the United Nations Relief and Rehabilitation Administration and Near East Foundation relief efforts in Greece from 1944-1946. The papers include correspondence, reports, and photographs, relating to social conditions and relief work in Greece at the end of World War II.
Administrative Information
Access
The collection is open for research
Access to audiovisual materials requires at least two weeks advance notice. Audiovisual materials include sound recordings, video recordings, and motion picture film. Hoover staff will determine whether use copies of the materials requested can be made available. Some materials may not be accessible even with advance notice. Please contact the Hoover Institution Archives Audiovisual Specialist for further information.
Acquisition Information
Materials were acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 2005
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Biographical Chronology
1908 Born, Wayne, Pennsylvania, known to friends and family as "Nancy"
1930-1943 Teacher, Lower School of the Shipley School, Bryn Mawr, Pennsylvania
1943 First expressed interest in working with World War II relief organizations
1944-1945 October Began working on a United Nations Relief and Rehabilitation Administration (UNRRA) funded project in rural Greece, and was supported by UNRRA through October 1945 while working for the Congregational Christian Service Committee.
1945 October - 1946 Began working for the Near East Foundation as Director of Child Welfare for the West Coast
1946 August Returned to the United States, married Clifton Lisle, and settled in Chester Springs, Pennsylvania for the rest of her life.
2001 November 3 Died, Chester Springs, Pennsylvania
Scope and Content of Collection
Anna Howell Hayward Lisle worked with the United Nations Relief and Rehabilitation Administration and Near East Foundation relief efforts in Greece from 1944-1946. The papers include correspondence, reports, and photographs, relating to social conditions and relief work in Greece at the end of World War II.
The documentation describes Lisle's work in Greece, focusing on the villages of Patras, Yannina, Konitsa, and Agrinion (not far from the boarder of Albania) where she was part of an effort to establish youth hostels that hosted local children and children from nearby mountainous regions for three-month periods. The children were bathed, given clothing, shoes, medicine, and inoculations. They were taught in schoolroom settings and nourished with a healthy diet. Lisle also collaborated with many charitable groups, including the General Federation of Women's Clubs, to obtain donations of clothing and other items for the Greek villagers. In addition, she studied the culture and diet of the region, as evidenced in her reports, notes, and correspondence.
Arrangement
The collection is organized into three series, Biographical Document, Photographs, and Greek Relief Work.
Indexing Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in Stanford University's online catalog.
Subjects
World War, 1939-1945, Civilian relief.; World War, 1939-1945, Greece.; International relief.; United Nations Relief and Rehabilitation Administration.; Near East Foundation.
Container List
- Biographical File, 1953-1957; circa 2001.
  Includes a bound document, created circa 2001 with biographical information and photocopies of correspondence from 1934-1957, training documentation, and general personal correspondence.
  - Biographical Document, circa 2001. (Box-folder 1: 1)
    Bound document with Biographical Information and photocopies of correspondence from 1934-1957
  - Training and Experience Document, circa 1943 (Folder 1: 2)
  - Correspondence (photocopies) unrelated to Greece, 1934-1957 (Folder 1: 3)
  - Relief of the Northern Provinces of Greece calendar, 1953 (Folder 1: 4)
  - Christmas cards and clippings, circa 1945-1950. (Folder 1: 5)
    Some cards include photographs of Greece
- Photographs, circa 1945-1946. (Box 1)
  Black and white prints and negatives of landscapes, villages, people, children, camps, youth hostels, and aid workers in Greece. Some photographs are labeled with the city Konitsa.
  - "Nancy" Anna Hayward Lisle with other aid workers, circa 1946 (Folder 1: 6)
  - Near East Foundation photograph album with captions, circa 1946 (Folder 1: 7)
  - Konitsa, Greece, prints and negatives, circa 1945-1946 (Box-folder 2: 1)
  - Greece, prints, circa 1945-1946 (Folder 2: 2-3)
  - Greece, prints and negatives, circa 1945-1946 (Folder 2: 4-5)
- Greek Relief Work, 1945-1950.
  Includes correspondence, reports, notes, and other documentation describing the social and economic conditions in Greece after World War II and the relief work conducted by organizations such as the United Nations Relief and Rehabilitation Administration (UNRRA) and the Near East Foundation
  - Notebook, 1945 (Folder 2: 6-8)
    (3 folders) Describes visits to villages
  - United Nations Relief and Rehabilitation Administration (UNRRA)
    - General, 1945 (Folder 2: 9)
    - Field and Headquarters visit reports, 1945 (Folder 2: 10)
    - Report on the problem of changing food habits, an analysis of the diet of a Macedonian peasant, undated (Folder 2: 11)
    - Personnel Information, 1945-1946 (Folder 2: 12)
    - Report on the General Situation of Zakynthos, circa 1946 (Folder 2: 13)
  - Near East Foundation
    - Reports and Correspondence, 1945-1950 (Box-folder 2: 14-16)
      (3 folders)
    - Publicity, 1945 (Folder 2: 17)
    - Brochures and photographs, circa 1945-1946 (Folder 2: 18)
    - Packages from USA, 1946 (Folder 2: 19)
    - Foreign Director's report, Fall 1946 (Folder 2: 20)